Guide to the David Townsend Mason Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Townsend Mason Papers
1907-1973
MS 545
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
The papers consist entirely of Mason's diaries and travel journals spanning the years 1907-1973. The sixty-eight volumes of diaries deal chiefly with forestry and give considerable attention to the formulation of national policy on forests in the 1930s. The fifteen travel diaries (1950-1972) record Mason's almost annual trips to Europe and the Far East and are also largely devoted to technical subjects.
Mason, David Townsend, 1883-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David T. Mason, 1966, and the Oregon Historical Society, 1976.
Existence and Location of Copies
Diaries from 1907-1936 are available on microfilm (3 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost: order no. HM46.
Scope and Contents
In 1966 David Townsend Mason gave to the Yale University Library 31 diaries for the years 1907-1936. These diaries may be found in boxes 1 and 2 of the papers. (HM film 46 was made from this accession.) In April 1976, Manuscripts and Archives received an additional 37 volumes of personal diaries spanning the years 1937-1973, and 15 volumes of travel journals of David Townsend Mason dating from 1950 to 1972.
The address that appears inside each diary is given in the listing which follows.
Biographical / Historical
David T. Mason (1883-1973): professor of forestry at the University of California, manager of the Western Pine Association, executive officer of the New Deal Lumber Code Authority, advocate of sustained-yield forestry management.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Art; Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forests and forestry; Asia; Europe -- Description and travel; Latin America; Soviet Union; West (U.S.); Diaries; Foresters; Mason, David Townsend, 1883-1973; Yale University. School of Forestry
- Inventory
  - Diaries
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Available on 3 microfilm reels
    - Grandin, Missouri (Bound Brook, New Jersey), 1907 May 7 - June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - United States Forest Service, (Washington, D.C.), 1907 July 1 - December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - United States Forest Service (Washington, D.C.), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - United States Forest Service (Missoula, Montana), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - United States Forest Service (Missoula, Montana), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - United States Forest Service (Anaconda, Montana), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Missoula, Montana, 1912, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Missoula, Montana, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - United States Forest Service (Missoula, Montana), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - University of California at Berkeley, California, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Berkeley, California, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David T. Mason, Captain, E.O.R.C. 10th Engineers (Bordeaux, France), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Division of Forestry, University of California, (Berkeley, California), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Forest Valuation Engineer, Timber Section, Bureau of Internal Revenue (Washington, D.C.), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Forestry, University of California (Berkeley, California), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 673 Johnson, Portland, Oregon, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland, Oregon. Business: Northwestern Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland, Oregon. Business: Northwestern Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland Oregon. Business: American Bank Building, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland Oregon, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland, Oregon. Business: 736 American Bank Building, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Western Pine Association, Yeon Building, Portland, Oregon, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 509 Myrtle St., Portland, Oregon, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Yeon Building, Portland, Oregon, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1337 Connecticut Avenue, Washington, D C., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Portland, Oregon, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Portland, Oregon, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1525 S.W. Myrtle St., Portland, Oregon. Business: American Bank Building, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1957-1964 (Box 4, Folder 18-21)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1965-1972 (Box 5, Folder 22-25)
    - American Bank Building, Portland, Oregon, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Travel Journals
    - "European Notes", 1950 May 14 - June 23 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - South America, 1951 December 28 - 1952 January 31 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Lima, Peru, 1952 February 1 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Europe, 1954 May 1 - June 26 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "Oriental Trip", 1955 October 9 - November 30 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Europe, 1958 May 11 - July 20 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - South Pacific, Australia, 1959 March 20 - May 22 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Hawaii, Japan, 1961 May 22 - June 20 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Philippines, 1964 April 5 - June 9 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Mexico, 1965 February 28 - March 31 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - "Empire Builder", various, Cairo, Massena, 1967 January 27 - April 12 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Italy, 1969 April 20 - May 22 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Russia, 1971 May 29 - July 12 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - South America, 1972 September 30 - November 2 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Europe, Undated [1947-1957?] (Box 6, Folder 32)